Dealing With People I Hate
(Questioner) Hello.
(Questioner) I am a woman
in my 30's living in Busan.
I initially wanted to ask
why the person I dislike is the way he is.
But, after listening to you, I wonder,
"Why am I this way?"
"Why do I dislike that person?"
Out of so many people
I meet throughout my life,
I wonder why I am so sensitive to
certain people and dislike them.
I wonder what kind of attitude
I should have.
That's your karma.
I am going to ask the audience a question.
Just observe how people are.
Please raise your hands if you like cats.
Raise your hands.
Look.
Put your hands down.
Please raise your hands
if you don't like cats.
(Audience laughter)
Put your hands down.
Please raise your hands if you like dogs.
Please raise your hands
if you don't like dogs.
See, there are about half of them.
Please raise your hands
if you like dog meat.
(Audience Laughter)
See, there are some.
So, starting with food...
I asked only a couple of questions, right?
Starting with food,
no one needs to like
the same things that you do.
Even when the whole world
loves a person, you may hate him.
hates a person, you may like him.
So, it's that way with
people, foods,
and countries.
It's that way with everything.
So, what do you call this?
It is called your karma.
So, why are people different,
having different personalities
and different tendencies?
They have different karma.
So, if you were raised in a household
eating salty foods,
you will end up eating saltier foods.
And if you didn't, you will eat blander foods.
So, if these two people get married,
they would fight over the foods being
salty or bland. "Can't you taste?"
The preferences come from your habits.
So, it's not a big deal.
You can't say someone's habits are
good or bad.
So there is no right or wrong,
there are only differences
And likes and dislikes
arise from the differences.
So, there is no basis for
liking something, or disliking something.
However it is reality that
you have preferences.
Just don't be constrained
by those feelings.
If you don't like something,
just don't do it.
No need to force yourself to do it,
Just because you don't like someone,
that doesn't mean he is a bad person.
It's only your karma.
Just because something tastes salty to you,
that doesn't mean it's actually salty.
Just because something tastes bland to you,
that doesn't mean it's actually bland.
Because someone else might
taste the same food differently.
The difference comes from your karma.
You all know that
everyone's bodies are different.
Tomatoes are tasty, but there are people
who are allergic to tomatoes.
Peaches are good,
but some people are allergic to them.
Have you heard of apple allergies?
Yes, so everyone's body is different.
It's because their bodies are
made up differently.
So, if you don't like someone,
just don't see that person.
But, that doesn't mean
he is a bad person.
Do you understand?
You may dislike someone,
but, that person might like you.
Doesn't that happen? Yes.
It's the preference of that person.
It's good when you and
someone like each other.
It's also a relief when dislike is mutual.
(Audience Laughter)
Conflicts arise when you like someone
who doesn't like you,
or vice versa.
Some people relentlessly chase you around
even when you don't like them, right?
There always are.
Although I don't think it's happened
to you. (Audience Laughter)
So, that's why there are conflicts.
So, while dealing with people like that,
we have to understand and
accept that it's due to our karma.
(Questioner) That's really hard...
dealing with them...
(Questioner) There are always people like
that in our lives.
So, practice is not being affected
by likes or dislikes.
If you understand this,
It's the same thing as
you go out to eat and they order pizza
even though you like pasta.
You are little unhappy.
If you have a choice,
between pizza and pasta,
you can order pasta.
But, if they order pizza for the
whole group, you just eat the pizza.
It's not a big deal.
Just eat a bit less.
(Audience Laughter)
If you complain why they only order
the pizza, and not give you the choice,
then you will feel unhappy.
Then life will be hard for you.
You just adapt to the given situation.
Just recognize character and
preferences of your and others.
There's nothing you can do about
his karma and the way he is.
If you can't accept this,
the world will be a hard place for you.
If you like apples, but,
live with a spouse who is allergic,
can you live together, or not?
You can't know everything about
the other person before you get married.
Then, you will have conflicts
every time you buy fruits.
But, we need to understand
each other in these situations.
You just have to make compromises.
You either, don't buy the apples
since he can't eat them,
or, he let you buy a few apples
since you like them.
So, as you see,
there will be conflicts between people
who are different
whether you know it or not.
Go ahead
if you have something else to say.
(Questioner) I have nothing to say.
(Sunim) In that case, sit down then.
(Audience Laughter and Applause)
You know, you can keep your
preferences and still live your life.
You just avoid the people
you dislike whenever possible.
If you do that, it will
limit your life a bit.
So, if you want to live with anyone,
under any condition,
you have to be less restricted by
your preferences, while considering them.
That's your choice.
You can hang on to your preferences,
or, you insist less on your preferences.
Then you would expand your social circle.
So, there is no good or bad choice.
If you want to be freer,
just don't be so stubborn
If you want to be stubborn
and stick to your preferences,
then you just sever your ties
with certain people.
If there's a person you dislike at work,
you just quit.
But, what's usually the problem?
You want to keep your job
because it pays well,
but, you hate your boss
so you want to quit.
That's when you agonize, right?
But, there is nothing to agonize over.
It's a matter of choice.
So, you just decide what to choose.
That's the way the world is.
(Applause)